<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[The Life of Fetzig]]></title><description><![CDATA[An adventure in illness, madness, and entering society.]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 03:58:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Dreams]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve always had a strange connection with my dreams.  Until very recently, I dreamed exclusively in nightmares.  At the same time, I almost never remember my dreams.  I knew they were nightmares because I woke up terrified, shaking, and sometimes too scared to look out from my covers to examine my room for a physical manifestation of whatever had just invaded my subconscious.  I was easily scared as a child, and because I didn’t remember my dreams, I never knew what was coming to get me.  I usually remembered a rush of noise, flashes of brightly lit and somehow unsettling colors, but nothing concrete.  Therefore, any misshapen shadow or unexplained noise could be perceived as something unknown creeping out of my nightmares into the living world.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Those are the first type of dreams I had and I still have them today and still consider them nightmares.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The second type of nightmare is the recurring ones.  These ones are everything the abstract nightmares aren’t.  They are clear, the danger is easily identifiable, and when I wake up I remember them vividly.  The difference is these ones are about things I’m actually afraid of in the living world, and so I don’t wake up terrified because they can’t get into my room.  They aren’t the unknown, they aren’t illogical and hard to describe.  In fact, according to most people, they aren’t even nightmare worthy.  I’ll eventually describe a couple to you and you can decide if that last bit is true or not.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve also always believed these recurring nightmares serve a purpose.  They aren’t always the exact same dream, but they’re variations on the original, and they happen at particular times in my life.  Like I said earlier, I feel weird about my dreams.  The abstract, immaterial ones scare the crap out of me, but I always eventually fall back asleep and they don’t affect me the next day at all.  The recurring ones wake me up and keep me awake thinking about them.  They affect my mindset about certain things, and they’ve even caused me to make life-altering decisions.  So they are important to me and when I have them I take them seriously.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>At the same time, I don’t believe in the mystical version of dream reading.  I don’t believe my dreams will tell my fortune or hold mystical truths about myself.  At the same time, my recurring nightmares are not “just dreams”.  They’re truths of a certain variety, maybe just in a form my mind can understand better when I’m sleeping.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The most popular recurring nightmare is something I call “The Tsunami Dream”.  I call it most popular because it happens the most often of all my recurring dreams.  In its original form, I’m standing on a beach, sometimes alone and sometimes with other people.  The first time I had it the beach was a familiar one, but it isn’t always.  In all versions of the dream, there is a beach and a cliff lining it.  This type of beach occurs in my hometown, but they’re common enough other places that you might know what I’m talking about.  Basically, there’s ocean, then sand, then a cliff, then the rest of the city or whatever.  That part is fuzzy in my dream because I never get there.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Anyway, I’m standing on a beach and there’s a cliff at my back and the ocean in front of me.  And in the ocean, coming towards me, is one of those towering movie tsunamis than don’t actually occur many places in real life and certainly don’t occur where I live.  You know those giant walls of water that defy gravity and ocean physics and every other law of the land?  It’s always one of those.  And there’s always a choice I have to make before the tsunami reaches me, and I can never make the choice.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The first time I had the dream I was fairly young, and the choice was do I gather my towel and stuff before I run away or not.  I remember this iteration of the dream vividly because I woke up feeling really stupid for having dreamed it.  But in the nightmare, I picked up, dropped, and picked up my towel several times in terrifying indecision before looking up to find the wave crashing over me.  And then I woke up.  I never have to dream through the aftermath of being swept away in a tsunami, but I always feel the crushing realization that I have waited too long to make my decision and there is no getting away from the wave now.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As you may have guessed, the tsunami dream always occurs when I’m feeling overwhelmed in life, and the decision corresponds terrifyingly with whatever is overwhelming me.  For example, when I first became sick with gastrparesis, before I was diagnosed, I babysat frequently for multiple families.  I love kids and I especially loved the kids I was sitting for at that time.  As I got sicker, I started falling behind the kids in energy and patience and became unable to continue sitting for most of my kids.  There was one family that I wouldn’t let go of though, because the boy had special needs and his sister was amazing and they entire family treated me like I was part of the family.  But I kept getting sicker and sicker without a diagnosis and the boy was quickly becoming too much for me to handle physically.  So, without warning, the tsunami dream resolved the situation by placing me on that familiar beach and placed the boy and his sister at opposite ends of the beach.  Which one do I save before the tsunami kills us all?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As usual, I couldn’t make that decision.  I woke up from that dream crying and quit babysitting for good the next day.  Not because I ever thought I would have to make that decision, but because I realized I wasn’t doing either of those children any good continuing to babysit them in the condition I was in.  In fact, I’m not going to be able to do any children any good in with the disease I have.  And even though I didn’t know at the time that I had a lifelong ailment, I knew I had to stop trying to help my kids until I figured out how to help myself.  And I didn’t have that thought until the tsunami dream made me face the facts about the situation.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>All that example is to say, I have a new recurring nightmare to contemplate and I haven’t figured out what it’s trying to affect.  I started having it when I moved away to Berkeley and it kind of pops up at random.  I had it last night, which is why I’m thinking about it today.  I’ve decided to call it “The Hallway Dream”.  In this dream, predictably, I’m always wandering through a series of hallways.  In the dream, I recognize the hallways as part of my childhood home.  They aren’t, and are never the same from dream to dream, but in the dream I am home.  But there’s something wrong, and dream me can never figure out what it is.  It’s like that scary movie tactic where they slightly skew the camera to unsettle the viewer without the viewer noticing.  The hallways aren’t skewed, but my dream self is slightly unsettled by something she’s seeing in the, to her, familiar hallways.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This nightmare is a weird one to me, because it’s not actually scary.  Thinking about it now, I’m just wandering some seemingly normal hallways.  There are doors, there are pictures and other things hung on the walls, and there’s light enough to see clearly.  But you notice I still call it a nightmare, because I am scared in the dream.  There’s something wrong and my dream persona doesn’t know what it is.  And because I haven’t figured what triggers this dream, I can’t really figure what’s wrong when I’m awake either.  I had it three or four times while I was in Berkeley, I had it once when I was living with my parents after I graduated, and now I’ve had it twice since living with Skoddie.  And I think I’ll continue having it until I figure out what it means.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/04/24/Dreams.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/04/24/Dreams.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Recurring Dreams]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Life]]></category><category><![CDATA[Nightmares]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Letter to my Gastroparesis]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I visited a therapist for the first time last week and had a good conversation about my illness and my mental state.  I’ve known for a long time now that grief is part of the process of chronic illness and acceptance of the illness is necessary to continue living a healthy life after diagnosis.  I’ve known this and I’ve fought it because I don’t want to accept gastroparesis into my life and I don’t want to be ok with it.  But that refusal is tearing me apart mentally, so I went to the therapist as the first step towards acceptance.  She thinks she can help me, which makes one of us, and I think I’m at least willing to try.  Her first instruction was to write a letter to my gastroparesis making use of a prompt she gave me to get started in the right direction.  The following is the letter I’ve written, which I will read to my therapist when I see her on Wednesday:</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Dear Gastroparesis,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I don’t like you.  I don’t like being forced to second guess every ingredient in a meal before I eat it.  I used to be willing to try anything once.  I used to enjoy walking into a restaurant and ordering the weird thing on the menu I’d never heard of.  And no matter what came out on my plate, I would eat it, and I would usually enjoy it.  I don’t like having to special order meals, I don’t like having to read every ingredient on the box before I buy food at the store, and I especially don’t like the uncertainty you cause when all this fails and I get sick anyway.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I resent you.  I resent having to give up my favorite foods and drinks because of you.  I will never get to order a large iced vanilla latte with extra cream because of you.  I will never taste the flavors of the world because of you.  I resent having to give up my favorite activities because of you.  I resent having to give up on my years of babysitting and childcare dreams because of you.  You exhaust me.  You weaken me.  You make me constantly sick.  I will never dance again because of you and for that, I resent you.  I resent the damage you have done to my body and my mind.  I resent you for forcing me to watch myself shrink until I had no weight left to lose and I resent you for the uphill battle to gain it all back.  And at the end of that battle, you have left me with crippling depression, anxiety, self-doubt, self-consciousness, a weak body image, and no hope of ever being the same and I resent you for all of it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I hate you.  I hate when you make me feel sick.  Physically and mentally, you make me feel sick and I hate it.  I hate that you make everything worse.  I caught a cold and you turned it into strep, and then you made the antibiotics impossible to stomach.  I heard about a flu outbreak on campus and you made me believe I had caught it and was going to die from it.  I’ve been sick for weeks because of what you’ve done to my body.  I hate that you ruined college for me.  I hate that my friends were all out partying while I stayed home and tried to fight you off.  I hate the word idiopathic, and I hate the hopelessness it inspires in me every time I think it.  I hate that it took my doctors years to name you, and even now that I know your name, I have no chance of ever defeating you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m fed up with you.  I’m fed up with your rules.  Every time I think I’ve found something safe you ruin it.  Every meal, there’s something wrong.  Every drink, I have to question it.  Is it too much spice?  Is it too much caffeine?  Too acidic?  Too much fiber?  Oh by the way, I still have to get my daily vitamins, and even those you ruin with your rules.  It’s too much or it’s too little or I’ve forgotten I can’t actually eat that because your rules say no.  All of your rules add up to no and I am fed up.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m tired of you.  I’m tired of going to sleep nauseous and waking up nauseous and being nauseous every moment in between and knowing it will be that way for the rest of my life.  You are so well known for the nausea and even vomiting doesn’t make it go away, it makes it worse.  It triggers the pains and the anxiety and the tears.  I’m tired of the abdominal pains, and I’m tired of not knowing what’s causing them or how to fix them.  Every twinge brings new doubts and fears.  What’s wrong with me now?  Oh it’s just you, back again to remind me my body isn’t my own anymore.  I’m tired of the anxiety after every meal.  Will I keep my food down this time?  Will I need to take more pills to keep you at bay?  And the pills, oh the pills.  Every one making me tired or dizzy or causing pain and they’re all because of you and I am tired of them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I want my life and my body back.  I used to be so very happy in my skin.  I used to be confident and beautiful and powerful.  I used to love being.  I was ready to face the world, good or bad, I was ready for it all.  I want that back.  I want to be able to get out of bed in the morning and smile.  I want to love being again.  I want to love myself again.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/04/03/A-Letter-to-my-Gastroparesis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/04/03/A-Letter-to-my-Gastroparesis.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Invisible Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Chronic Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Therapy]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[On My Current Body Image]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is probably going to get into touchy territory for some people, but it’s something I need to get out.  So read my tags and if you can’t handle those topics, feel free not to read.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve been at war with my body for the better part of the last two years.  I mean mentally, physically, in all sense of the phrase, I am at war.  I hate my body.  I hate everything about it.  I hate everything it is doing.  I hate everything I have to deal with because of it.  And I hate myself for hating my body because I used to love it so much.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The day I got sick I weighed 165 pounds.  It was my fourth semester of taking ballet classes and my second semester of Pilates at my college and the women who taught the classes made every second worth it, which meant I was in great shape.  I don’t mean six-pack having, weight–lifting shape.  I mean I felt great.  I felt comfortable in my body.  I wasn’t model thin but I felt like I looked good.  I was happy.  Everything was in balance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The day I got sick my body betrayed me.  As far as anyone can tell me, my stomach just up and quit its job.  It took two years of testing and poking and prodding to prove to me that there was nothing wrong with me other than my stomach just didn’t work anymore.  No one I’ve seen has any clue why.  It was a slow transformation in my mind, but I went from loving everything about the body I was in, to hating every inch of it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I started out by trying to placate my new condition.  I’ve been following the diet as far as I could find on forums and support groups online.  I cut almost all of my favorite foods out of my diet, I spent a lot of time trying to decide which vitamin supplements would help and which would harm, I stuck to a fairly strict rice-based diet.  Easy to digest, soft foods, liquids frequently.  I tried everything.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But even though I knew exactly what was wrong with me and what I was supposed to do to help make it better, almost nothing worked.  I’m on one of the most dangerous drugs on the market to help stimulate the muscles of my digestive system, I’m on the blandest diet possible, I eat smaller meals less frequently, and I’m still nauseous.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am nauseous all the time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And at some point, I decided I was fucking done with it.  My body, which I had loved and cared for as much as possible, continued to betray me.  I continued to lose weight, I sunk further into depression, I went mildly insane, my hands shook, my vision fogged, I developed migraines and headaches, and I deteriorated and deteriorated.  I hated it.  My body has betrayed me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And so I went to war.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve gone back and forth in my mind on whether or not I have an eating disorder or if I’m just suicidal.  The short of it is that it’s easier to just not eat.  I don’t usually wake up nauseous, it’s just when I add food, so some days I don’t.  Because then my body can’t let me down.  My stomach can’t fail me if I don’t put anything in it.  And it’s not fear of the nausea, it’s rage.  It’s anger and resentment that I have to deal with this bullshit everyday without relief.  I don’t get a break.  There are some days I only eat due to Skoddie’s prodding.  Some days I eat because I feel bad about what I’m doing to myself.  Some days I just don’t eat.  But at the same time, I’m not going to starve to death.  I&#8217;m actually gaining weight somehow.  So am I developing an eating disorder or am I suicidal?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Or am I just angry?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My therapist thinks I’m grieving.  She thinks I can move past the anger and her first instruction was to write a letter to my gastroparesis explaining what I hate/resent about it.  But I don’t know if I can separate the two.  Do I write to my gastroparesis or do I write to my stomach directly?  Do I ask it why it just decided to stop working one day without warning or reason?  Do I ask it if I did something to trigger this?  It’s an argument I’ve been having in my mind since I was diagnosed.  It’s an anger I’ve had since I heard the word “idiopathic” attached to my illness.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m not sure if this post makes sense in the way I wanted it to.  But this is what I mean when I say I hate my body.  I hate what it’s doing to me.  I hate what it’s turned into.  It’s not about weight, or shape, or color.  It’s about the betrayal I feel deep inside when I think about what I could have been if I didn’t wake up nauseous that day in 2013.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/03/31/On-My-Current-Body-Image.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/03/31/On-My-Current-Body-Image.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Invisible Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Eating Disorders]]></category><category><![CDATA[Body Positivity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Suicide]]></category><category><![CDATA[Chronic Illness]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Things I Can’t Do]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Denial, Anger, Bargaining, Depression, and Acceptance.  These are what are known as the Five Stages of Grief, or the Five Stages of Dying depending on the situation and who you are talking to.  Basically, people who have lost or are going to lose a loved one are thought to go through these stages of emotion as they process the loss.  According to some psychologists and doctors, these stages are also relevant to people who find out they are dying, or are diagnosed with a life-changing illness or injury.  People who are paralyzed, people who have terminal cancer, people who lose a limb, the list is endless.  Many of these types of people are thought to go through this process of mourning the life they had before their particular disability or illness changed it.  It is thought to be the most healthy and common progression.  A person may not go through all the stages, and may even regress to a previous one after moving forward, but this progression is generally accepted as the norm.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I have been placed squarely in the anger category, though I experience bouts of depression augmented by my actual depression.  My denial phase was mostly spent in search of a cause of my illness.  I was in denial that this was a lifelong affliction, and I was in denial that I would never be able to go back to the way I was before.  I thought, if only I could find the cause, the doctors could fix it, my gastroparesis would go away, and everything would be great again.  I daydreamed about celebrating over double bacon cheeseburgers and root beer floats.  Even when two different specialists in two different cities told me idiopathic meant forever, I fought it.  I requested extra tests.  I spent days researching potential causes and comparing them to my symptoms.  I because very good friends with the librarians at my university.  I may have spent more time researching my disease than I did on work for my degree.  In the end the only knowledge I gained was that my life would never be the same again, and my dreams of living happily ever after had to be shelved with the rest of the fairy tales.  And that’s when I got angry.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Last night I attended the first annual Wastelander’s Ball.  This event is an off-shoot of a larger annual event called Wasteland Weekend.  Wasteland Weekend is a post-apocalyptic themed gathering based mostly around the Mad Max series, though it incorporates themes from other post-apoc stories as well.  It’s similar to a music festival like Coachella, except there are attractions other than music.  They set up a Thunderdome, there is a parade, there is food and bar areas, camping areas, and many apocalyptic themed groups and acts, all assembled in the middle of the desert in California for a few days.  I have known about Wasteland for a few years and have been interested in attending basically since I heard of it, but never knew if I would be able to handle such an event.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So the Ball last night was a good chance to test out my endurance.  The theme was enforced, so you were to attend in your best post-apoc formal wear, many of the people who attend Wasteland Weekend were there, and some of the talent and music acts performed as well.  I spent a few days putting together a costume with the help of friends and attended the Ball with my wife.  I spent the weeks leading up to it thinking it wouldn’t be too strenuous, I would meet some of the people from Wasteland, and see if I wanted to actually attend the festival.  But about halfway through the night, my stomach began to hurt.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>One of the symptoms of gastroparesis is abdominal pains and bloating, something I can usually avoid by eating the proper foods and not working too hard.  But there is a special kind of pain I have begun to associate with over-exertion which I haven’t figured out how to avoid and can only be resolved by a full night of sleep.  It’s a sharp burning pain right below my sternum which, if unchecked, radiates throughout my abdomen.  Oddly, it is one of the few pains I experience which is not accompanied by nausea, but the pain can reach a 5 or 6 on the 10 point pain scale if I let it go long enough.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is the kind of pain that assaulted me last night halfway through the Ball, and, at that point, I began to get angry and depressed.  I associate this pain with the ballet classes I took in college, walking too fast or far while Frisbee golfing, and the rare times I have attempted to really exercise since the onset of my illness.  I don’t associate it with sedately walking around a small restaurant in comfortable shoes and frequently taking breaks to meet and talk to people.  Which is why it made me angry.  I still have a little bit of that petulant child in me, that little voice in the back of my head that says, “but that’s not fair!”  I did everything right yesterday.  I ate simple and small meals like I’m supposed to, I made sure my costume wasn’t restricting or too heavy, I drank plenty of water, and I was still awarded with this burning pain.  The signal that my body was done with whatever I was doing, even if I wasn’t.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And the rage stems from a few places.  It’s rage against my new restrictions, things my body is deciding without reason or warning.  I avoided creating a costume that cinched in around the middle, a style I find much more attractive than what I ended up wearing, because I knew putting physical pressure on my abdomen would upset my stomach.  I don’t get to wear corsetry anymore.  I avoided solid foods and large meals because I know eating too much would put pressure on my digestive system.  I couldn’t eat the food provided at the venue, I had to eat beforehand, and I had to eat something bland and soupy.  I couldn’t wear heels, my preferred shoe for a formal event, because I wanted my body to be comfortable and secure.  And even with all these precautions, I couldn’t do the one thing I wanted to do at the Ball.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I couldn’t dance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>By the time the music started and everyone was on the dance floor, I was huddled in a corner wishing I could just rip my stomach out and toss it to the birds.  I can’t attend an event like the Wastelander’s Ball and participate in the main attraction.  I probably can’t go to Wasteland Weekend for the same reason.  Even with all my precautions and medications and doctors, I can’t go have fun with everyone else.  I can only sit on the sidelines and watch the party.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And that is what the rest of my life looks like</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And that is why I am stuck at Anger.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/02/26/Things-I-Cant-Do.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/02/26/Things-I-Cant-Do.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Invisible Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Disabilities]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[In Defense of Rage]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I went to my new doctor yesterday.  I was forced to switch after graduating, moving back to my hometown, getting married, and switching to a new insurance company.  This whole thing with my stomach started in 2013 and since then, I’ve switched doctors and specialists at least 15 times.  Over the course of those transfers I’ve been accused of a lot of things.  I’ve had doctors tell me I’m anorexic.  I’ve had doctors accuse me of seeking drugs.  I’ve had doctors call me alcoholic and irresponsible and not worthy of their care.  So I approached this new doctor with trepidation and the thought process that I need to be prepared.  I showed up 20 minutes early with copies of my most recent blood work, gastric empting study, endoscope, and a cheat sheet of all my medications, dosages, and past doctor’s offices and contact information.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And she was the nicest, most sympathetic doctor I’ve ever spoken to.  She admitted she’d never had a patient with idiopathic gastroparesis so young and therefore wanted to hear my whole story from beginning to end.  I told her everything, I showed her my test results and paperwork, and answered her follow-up questions to the best of my ability.  And at some point I must have said or done something light-hearted because she commented on how well-adjusted and accepting of my illness I seem and how impressed she was by it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In reality, I’m not any of those things and I tend to get really confused when people think I am.  The truth is, I spend most of my days oscillating between rage and apathy so deep I can’t get out of bed.  And the rage is easier for me to deal with.  The rage gives me something to work with.  When I’m mad I can say no fuck this and get myself going until I get too mad and then I shut down into apathy for a while.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m going to outline the thought process behind that rage/apathy spiral via an example.  Before I got sick, I was introduced to the magical gift of food that is called pho.  Really, all Vietnamese food, but for the purposes of this rant I’m specifying pho and Thai iced tea, which is some kind of black tea with cream in it and is basically the best drink I’ve ever put in my mouth.  When combined with a nice bowl of pho, it is the meal of gods and I ate it almost every day.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now, pho is basically just rice noodles in beef broth, sometimes with different cuts of meat and veggies added.  It is worth saying that I can, and still do, eat it very often.  But once I started getting sick I noticed a correlation with highly caffeinated drinks and my nausea and stopped drinking caffeine.  Once I was diagnosed, I learned it’s actually a specific type of acid in caffeinated drinks like coffee and tea that upsets my already sensitive stomach and causes nausea.  It’s not actually affecting the emptying of my stomach, it’s just irritating my system enough to cause nausea.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Skip to now, somewhere between four and five years after the onset of symptoms and about two years after the diagnosis of my gastroparesis, I decided to experiment with caffeine again.  My thought process was, before, the acid was irritating my already irritated stomach and digestive system.  Now, I’m on all kinds of medication and I wanted to see if I could handle these acidic caffeinated teas.  I started slow with green tea mixed with ginger tea, then plain green tea, and both seemed to go down just fine.  So, in my over confident and eternally optimistic mind, I decided to attempt my very favorite food and tea combo the next time I went for pho.  This happened this week on Tuesday, and then again tonight.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On Tuesday, all went moderately well.  My stomach was a little upset, but it’s honestly been worse and I figured if that was all I had to deal with in order to drink my very favorite drink in the world, I would live.  Tonight, I hardly made it out of the restaurant before I was hit with burning stomach pains and the overwhelming urge to vomit up everything I had just eaten and drank, including my tea.  I ended up taking three different medications, two of which are for emergencies only, in order to keep my food down and make it home.  And somewhere over the course of driving home, I got pissed off.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I used to love food and eating.  Trying different kinds of food was my favorite thing in the world.  I was by no means a foodie, but I would basically try anything once.  I had a friend who would take me to all her random food spots and we’d eat all kinds of random shit together and those were honestly my favorite days.  I used to spend all my money on random food.  I would go over to other people’s houses and eat their random homemade food and love my life.  It was great.  Food is the best part of life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So imagine my fucking rage when I was diagnosed with an illness that basically limited my food options to the blandest, most easy to digest, most boring meals in the world.  For the rest of my life.  I have been mad for years, and nothing anyone says or does makes me less so.  I realize that being angry at God, the queen, and everyone in between is not going to fix anything but that’s where the apathy comes in.  I get so mad I could jump off a bridge and my only thought on the way down would be “Thank God I don’t have to take another fucking pill for the rest of my life”.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I literally shut down.  I got so mad the other night, at a matter unrelated to my Thai tea dilemma, that I sat on the couch with a blanket over my head and fumed for hours.  I had to have a blanket over my head because I’ll pretty much get mad enough that seeing or interacting with anything else will set me into an extremely violent and toxic rage spiral.  I try to avoid it.  I’m staving that off right now by writing this post and watching nail polish tutorials.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am that level of enraged by the realization that I can probably never drink Thai tea ever again for the rest of my life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And a lot of people will surely say this is counter-productive to my mental health and the acceptance process.  In fact, people have already told me this.  There’s a mourning process you go through when diagnosed with an illness like this and anger is just one step in the process.  You eventually have to come to terms and move on and not be constantly mad at life, this is immature, etc.  And maybe I’ll reach that point of acceptance and maturity at some point in my life.  But for now, I stand in defense of my rage.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/02/10/In-Defense-of-Rage.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/02/10/In-Defense-of-Rage.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Invisible Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anger]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[In Which I Offend all of my Well-Wishers]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>There’s this weird succession that occurs when you become sick and start losing weight.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First, there’s a lag while news spreads that you are ill.  During this time, well-meaning people begin congratulating you on your weight loss, thinking it was intentional and desired.  They believe, like so many others in society, that you were not happy with your body originally and that now you are fixing it.  So they congratulate you.  This phase lasted for about two months of my illness.  That was about the first 40 pounds of weight loss.  While I starved, friends and family came to me smiling and hugged me and said I looked great and good job on the weight loss.  The problem is, during this time period in the illness, I didn’t know how to tell them they were wrong.  I had no diagnosis, I had no answers, and I had multiple doctors accusing me of anorexia.  So I smiled and thanked them for the compliment and let the news spread naturally.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Second, there’s the collective realization and mourning of your illness, followed by the commentary about how skinny you’ve become and the questions about how you’re going to manage your illness.  This phase of my illness lasted about a year and a half, when my weight dipped into double digits and those who saw me on a regular basis realized it wasn’t intentional and something was wrong.  During this period, I still didn’t have a diagnosis, I didn’t have a reliable way to stop the nausea or the weight loss, and I didn’t have a way to express to those around me that I really wished they would stop telling me how worried about me they were.  I can guarantee, I was way more worried than anyone else involved in the project, and the constant reminder that everyone in my life was basically watching me die wasn’t in anyway helpful.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Third, if you are lucky, there’s the collective relief of a diagnosis and regaining the weight.  This phase is characterized by everyone in your life coming to tell you how happy they are that you’re getting better, how much healthier you look, and oh by the way have you tried X insane diet because my brother’s friend’s wife thinks it’s really good for you and you should try it.  This is the final phase and is currently ongoing.  This phase is characterized by long conversations with everyone who has been paying attention during the last two phases, educating them on the illness that is killing you, listening to their unsolicited medical advice with a smile on your face, and walking away feeling like shit about your body.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Here’s the thing about me and my body image.  I never had a problem with my body or my weight or anything like that until I got sick.  A lot of adolescent girls go through a period of body hate and insecurity where they get really uncomfortable with their bodies and how they look.  We are socialized from a young age to believe we are too fat, too thin, too pimply, too pale, too dark, and any number of other “too much” things.  Everything is wrong with our bodies and the fashion and beauty industries offer us many expensive and time consuming solutions to these “too much” problems.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But I never believed them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I wasn’t ever a paragon of self-confidence, but I was always at least comfortable in my skin.  My issues were always internal.  I was more worried about whether or not people perceived me as a bitch than whether or not they thought I was fat.  I’m not placing myself above those girls who go through those problems at all though.  I just never understood the fascination with makeup and beauty products and never used them.  I was working on my personality instead.  So imagine my surprise when my entirely dependable and beautiful body revolted, transformed, and turned into an enemy.  My stomach no longer works.  I can count my ribs.  I literally almost starved to death before we finally figured out what was wrong with me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m reading a book right now about the science of sex and arousal and the female body and I reached a part where the author relays a story about a recent mother who breaks down crying because she now has to figure out a way to love her body again after birth.  Her friends assure her she is beautiful, but she tells the author those reassurances made her feel worse about feeling bad about her body to begin with.  So maybe people who have given birth can relate to how I feel now that all my friends come running up to tell me how good I look now.  Maybe those who have suffered from eating disorders can understand.  Maybe other chronic illness sufferers can understand.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But if you’ve never suffered, there is no way for me to explain the deep and utter loathing I experience towards my body at this point in my life.  And part of that loathing came from the scrutiny I faced while my body was going through this transformation I never wanted.  It came from everyone telling me I looked lovely or healthy or too skinny or sick while my body internally revolted and decided to self-destruct without my permission.  I came from the juxtaposition of my hatred of my illness and society’s praises of my losses.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Like the pregnant woman in the book I’m reading, all I want is for everyone to stop reassuring me I look fine, and start telling me it’s ok to be angry at my body for changing.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Society hammers us with messages that our bodies are not pretty enough and not smooth enough and them when we finally believe them, society says, “No, you’re fine, why would you think that?”  Our body hatred stems from society’s reactions to transformations and changes which are sometimes out of our control.  At the height of my weight loss, when I weighed 90 pounds, I would sit in my room counting my ribs and cry for hours.  And then I would leave my bubble of self hatred to be told I looked so skinny and good.  Or someone would ask if I was ok because I looked so ill.  And I would return to my bubble and count my ribs and play those comments over and over in my head, and I finally came to the realization that my body is wrong or was wrong and I’ve never been enough and that’s why everyone waited until I got sick to comment on it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I don’t have a solution to this problem, other than to ask people to stop commenting on each others’ weights and body changes.  But will that help?  Will that cure my self-hatred?  Will that make our little girls feel better about their acne?  Will it make our pregnant mothers ok with the changing landscape of their bodies?  I don’t think that’s all there is to it.  But, it’s sure a start.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/01/05/In-Which-I-Offend-all-of-my-Well-Wishers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2017/01/05/In-Which-I-Offend-all-of-my-Well-Wishers.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Body Positivity]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fetzig and Milkshakes]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>A lot of my life revolves around my anxiety, and a lot of people don’t really understand what that means.  If you’ve never experienced an anxiety disorder, you don’t know what that means.  There’s a difference between stress and anxiety, and there’s a difference between momentary anxiety and the type a disorder causes.  That’s not to say one person’s anxiety is more or less valid than another’s.  They’re just different.  The daily anxiety I experience is different than the anxiety you experience when you failed to study for a test, which is different than the stress you feel while doing your math homework.  It’s possible to feel all of these types of anxiety at once and it’s possible to feel only one.  I’m just saying a lot of people don’t understand what a medically diagnosed anxiety disorder entails.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When I named this blog, I didn’t just pull Fetzig out of thin air.  I named my anxiety a little over a year ago during a conversation with my fiancée.  I named her, I created a personality for her, and I set her aside in her own place in my mind.  It was important at that time for me to realize that Fetzig is a different entity entirely.  She is a part of me, but she is not me.  I had to figure out a way to keep her from defining my life.  Naming her and giving her a space to sit was how I dealt with the situation, and it’s been fairly successful so far.  I think of my daily anxiety as Fetzig, the overprotective, jumpy, nagging roommate who cosigned the lease on my brain.  And living with her isn’t easy, but it’s easier than having the official words General Anxiety Disorder looming over my life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I call Fetzig overprotective because she gets upset about things that she perceives to be threats to my physical and mental health.  I say she perceives the threats because these are things that I, the sane part of my psyche, know aren’t actually dangerous.  Things like soda and milkshake machines.  There are a lot of those articles going around the internet titled things like “Foods You Should Never Order at Fast Food Restaurants”.  They’re usually lists or click-bait pages that have originated from Redit threads where people talk about all the horrible things they’ve witnessed wherever they were working or eating.  Something that is always on those lists are soda dispensers and milkshake makers, because they can have horrible bacterial growths if not cleaned properly.  If you listen to the internet, and Fetzig, no one ever cleans those machines and you should never drink anything that comes out of them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The problem with articles like that, other than them being extremely inaccruate, is that Fetzig latches onto them and never lets go.  And the problem with labeling milkshakes as dangerous is, believe it or not, they are on every diet list I’ve ever seen for Gastroparesis.  In moderation, they’re a really good source of easy to digest calories and calcium for someone with stomach problems if you can handle dairy.  Depending on what kind of stomach day I’m having, a milkshake is sometimes all I can manage for dinner.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There was a night about a month ago that I walked out of class, got into my car, and started contemplating what I would have for dinner as I drove home from school.  I was craving something substantive, but my stomach had been acting up that day so I didn’t want to eat anything too big or hard to digest.  I decided a milkshake and some fries from Jack in the Box would be the best thing for the conditions and rerouted to the nearest restaurant to grab dinner before I went to the house.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On the way there, I started hearing Fetzig’s voice in my head.  What about that article you read the other day?  That guy said he worked at a popular fast food chain and they never cleaned their shake machine.  What if this Jack in the Box is the same?  You’re going to get sick.  You shouldn’t get the shake.  It’s not safe.  You shouldn&#8217;t even eat here.  How often do they change their fry oil?  You&#8217;ll never know.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I pulled into the parking lot arguing reason with myself.  I even got my Skoddie in on the matter.  I parked and started texting her while trying to convince myself that of course they clean their machines because health code restrictions.  Before long, Skoddie is trying to talk me out of a full blown anxiety attack via text in a Jack in the Box parking lot.  I don’t know if she remembered that conversation we had a year ago, but she was attempting to reason with Fetzig whether or not she realized it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I sat in my car for a good 15 minutes before Skoddie suggested I go looking for the restaurant’s health code certifications.  Where I’m from in Southern California, those ratings are prominently displayed as large colored letter grades in the windows of the eatery in question.  So, thinking this will surely calm my mind, I start walking around this little fast food place looking for something similar.  Seeing nothing on the outside windows, I spend a little time peering into the place looking for a grade posted inside.  No such luck, I return to my car with Fetzig in my brain triumphantly shouting.  See, there’s no certification grade.  This must not be a good place to eat.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m in my car ready to never eat out again when Skoddie points out that grading system is regional.  In Berkeley, it might be different.  So once again, determined to prove to Fetzig that my milkshake is going to be drinkable, I go back to the windows and start looking for any kind of official looking documentation.  I don’t even think about going inside to ask.  Hello underpaid cashier, please humor my insanity by proving to me you and your coworkers comply with health codes and keep your milkshake machines cleaned properly.  No way.  Instead, I spend ten minutes peering through the windows like a weirdo until I finally spot some official looking documents posted next to the cash registers.  These turn out to be the proof of inspection papers I was seeking.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As strange as it sounds, this wasn’t the end of Fetzig for the night.  I spend a few more minutes texting with Skoddie before I feel comfortable enough going through the drive-thru and ordering my dinner.  And even as I’m drinking my milkshake, I hear Fetzig’s voice in my head numbering all the symptoms of food poisoning.  And oddly similar list to my usual Gastroparesis symptoms.  I didn’t end up developing food poisoning, but even that wasn’t the end of Fetzig’s opinion on the matter.  Every time I return to that place to get a milkshake, she’s in my head telling me about that article we read and all the bad things that grow in sugary environments.  I heard her tonight when I went there for a milkshake and fries again.  She was easier to ignore today, but I still heard her.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But it’s hard to view Fetzig as a harmful part of my psyche.  Like I said, she’s just being way over protective.  Maybe someday she’ll keep me from actually getting sick.  I’m not sure she’s been useful in that regard so far, but I’ll never actually know.  She’s the voice that makes me wash the tops of my cans of soup before I open them even though the Mythbusters proved that myth highly unlikely.  Her voice is the one that made me afraid of caffeinated green tea for almost a year, and she continues to keep me from trying sushi even though all sources point to it being really good for you and easy to digest.  She’s the over-active conspiracy theorist living in a corner of my brain.  Her voice is really loud some days and a whisper others.  She’s really easy to ignore some days and harder to overcome others.  But her voice is always there.  She is always there.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That is what it’s like living with an anxiety disorder.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/12/06/Fetzig-and-Milkshakes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/12/06/Fetzig-and-Milkshakes.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category><category><![CDATA[Anxiety]]></category><category><![CDATA[Fetzig]]></category><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Little Unsteady]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>When I first thought of starting a blog, I knew there was a possibility of it being a chronicle of my descent into insanity.  I know that sounds dramatic, but in all honesty there is a very real chance of me not coming out of this illness intact.  Whether it be physically or mentally, I am going to lose something.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m thinking about this today because I haven’t been doing well mentally.  My depression has been steadily increasing for the last two weeks, and there’s not much I can do but attempt to ride it out.  I got a brief bit of lift over Thanksgiving with my fiancée, but as soon as she went home I dropped right back into my little pit.  I spent this past weekend staring at a blank word document, forcing myself to do research for a paper, and crying.  And today wasn’t much better.  The paper is due Wednesday at 9AM and instead I find myself compelled to attempt to put something into words I don’t really understand myself.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This morning I woke up for class and I felt shaky.  In my head.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It doesn’t really make sense when I say it like that.  It felt like I was pulling apart at the seams.  I walked around the house making tea, eating breakfast and such, and the whole time I wondered if I was actually shaking.  I wasn’t, but I still drove to school with my arm wrapped around my stomach as if I could hold myself together that way.  I wasn’t any more nauseous than I usually am, and I wasn’t particularly tired.  I just wasn’t all there.  I sat in the car in the parking garage and just tried to breathe and steady myself.  I felt oddly calm otherwise.  There was no anxiety, no signs that I could see anything wrong.  I just couldn’t put myself back together.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Eventually, I had to walk to class.  I checked every so often to make sure I wasn’t actually outwardly shaking.   I hugged my tea to my chest and avoided eye contact as much as possible.  At some point, I realized I was crying again.  I stopped in a bathroom to fix the issue as best as possible.  The alarmed look I received from another student there would have spoken volumes if I could understand what she saw in my appearance.  She cut across the hall to avoid walking near me.  I felt a little more unsteady.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But looking in the mirror before class, I couldn’t see what she saw.  Tears removed, I looked like a completely normal, although tired, college student.  Still, one of my friends in class took one look at me and was immediately concerned.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>“You look like you’ve had the soul sucked out of you.”</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My reflexive smile didn’t reach my eyes.  I could tell he wasn’t reassured.  I mumbled something about being tired and went back to avoiding eye contact.  As I sat in class and went through the motions, I felt like something I was doing betrayed my mental state.  My friend seemed to glance over at me more often than usual, my professor’s gaze seemed concerned, and I felt panic ticking closer every moment I sat there trying to listen to her lecture.  I don’t know if any of this was real.  I imagined my classmates watching me fall apart over and over in that hour of class.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The drive home is what triggered it.  It takes 15 minutes to drive from Downtown Berkeley to the house I’m staying at.  That 15 minute drive turned into a nightmare of anxiety.  I had become hungry, my hands started shaking, and I began to imagine the jerking motions everyone on Reglan is told to look out for.  The world around me became blurry, the sounds deadened, and I started to sweat in 60 degree weather.  I was having the panic attack I had staved off during class on the road home.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Being the completely logical and sane human being that I am, I kept driving.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I can’t tell you why my brain went to Dory from Finding Nemo in that moment.  Just keep swimming.  It’s happened once before.  I was driving home from a party, before I had gotten sick, and I suddenly realized I was way too drunk to be driving.  I wasn’t swerving, I wasn’t going off the road, and I wasn’t speeding.  A realization just broke over me.  I had no idea how any of that was happening.  I was wasted and terrified and on the freeway halfway home.  And my completely irresponsible response was to just keep going.  Just keep swimming.  The one and only time I drove drunk by the way.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My panic response seems to be just keep going.  Pretend everything is normal until you make it to a safe space.  I’m apparently very good at it.  I fell apart on the drive home today.  I started crying, I got nauseous, I couldn’t breathe, and my mind just abandoned me.  Everything blurred together though I could see the road fine.  I took deep breaths and felt like I was suffocating.  My entire body began shaking but my hands somehow stayed steady.  I started to believe the world was falling apart around me.  I can’t begin to accurately describe it to you.  It felt like I was actually going insane.  I had a total meltdown on the drive home, pulled into a parking spot in front of my house, took a final deep breath, and it was over.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve spent the rest of today in bed contemplating that moment.  The moment it felt like I was literally losing my mind.  Coming apart at the seams is the only way I can describe it.  If you’ve ever seen someone take a piece of sewing and pull at the two pieces until the stitches holding them together gradually become visible, you know what I’m talking about.  Even the best made pieces come apart with enough pressure.  Sometimes the stitches are loose enough that the thread just pulls apart, and sometimes it just breaks.  But everything pulls apart with enough pressure.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I don’t really know why I feel compelled to share today’s story.  I usually feel like something can be gained from my struggles, but today just feels pointless.  Maybe I could have avoided the panic attack by not going to class.  Maybe it would have just been worse when it finally happened.  Even after some food and a short nap, I’m feeling unsteady.  My brain feels shaky.  My seams feel loose.  I have work to do if I want to graduate though.  I really identify with Dory on days like today.  Find the strength, find the will, and find a way.  Maybe the point is just keep swimming.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I don’t know.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/28/A-Little-Unsteady.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/28/A-Little-Unsteady.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><category><![CDATA[Panic Attacks]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[It Gets Better]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>This post is going to offend some people.  This post is going to make some people uncomfortable.  If you experience either of those emotions, this post is for you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>At the same time, this post is going to resonate with some people.  Maybe this post will even help some people.  This post is for you too.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This semester has been a hard one.  It’s been hard mentally and emotionally. One of the things they didn’t tell me when they diagnosed me was that gastroparesis can have a serious effect on your mental health.  They didn’t tell me that my previous minor psychological problems could be multiplied.  They didn’t tell me that an imbalance in my hormonal centers could form.  They don’t tell you all this when they diagnose you with chronic illness because they don’t want it to become a self-fulfilling prophecy.  Unfortunately, that approach leaves those of us who develop those serious mental illnesses completely unprepared.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I had some issues before I got sick.  I was bullied pretty hard when I was young, my family’s emotional support situation was not ideal, and I grew up with a lot of emotional baggage.  Had I made it to adulthood unscathed, maybe all I would have needed is a bit of therapy and a good support system to work through it.  On the other hand, maybe the depression was always in there anyway.  I’ll never know.  I do know that when I got physically sick, I got mentally sick as well.  And I was unprepared.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve spent most of today in bed thinking about the phrase “it gets better” and the campaigns and social movements surrounding it.  Most of these are aimed at depressed and suicidal individuals with the thought process that if only we believe hard enough for long enough, all of our problems will eventually get better.  Through hard work or divine intervention, it will get better.  Here’s the problem with that slogan.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>True or not, clinically depressed individuals cannot comprehend that statement.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That campaign stems from a fundamental misunderstanding of what depression actually is.  It works for moody teenagers and temporarily suicidal college students, because, for them, it truly will get better.  Failing a final will not ruin your entire life.  Breaking up with a partner hurts, but the resulting depression is temporary and will heal with the pain.  For a lot of people, it will get better if they wait long enough or try hard enough.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Someone with clinical depression suffers from a break down within the brain.  Certain nerves and glands misfire, certain hormones are not exchanged properly, or certain receptors just don’t work.  There’s a lot of science behind it, and honestly they don’t really understand it completely.  That’s why mental health patients often have to cycle through drugs and dosages before landing on the ones that work for them.  The short of it is depression is a physical failing that creates an uncontrollable mental and emotional imbalance.  And, often, it does not get better.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Take mine for example.  A possibly preexisting imbalance that was triggered or worsened by the onset of a chronic physical illness.  I’ve had two psychologists confirm this is not just the moody blues.  I have developed full-blown clinical depression.  And, not matter how hard I pray or how many drugs I take, it will not go away.  Our current medical approach to depression is incurable.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It will not get better.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Not only will it not get better, people telling me it will actually makes it worse.  It gets better means I didn’t try hard enough.  It gets better puts the fault on me.  It means that today, when I was unable to force myself to get out of bed, I was just being lazy.  I was the one who didn’t try hard enough.  I didn’t have the gumption to feed or dress myself.  I didn’t want to be ok bad enough.  That’s what you tell a clinically depressed person when you say “it gets better”.  That’s not what you meant?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It doesn’t matter.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Talking to a depressed person about the future is the greatest exercise in futility I have ever witnessed.  I don’t remember the past days when I was happy and care-free.  I know they existed.  I have pictures.  But I don’t remember those emotions.  Similarly, I can’t see a future in which I am happy again.  I don’t know how to feel that emotion anymore.  I can’t even visualize it right now as I’m writing about it.  My life is zeroed in on today and right now and how I’m feeling and what I’m doing right that moment.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And usually, how I’m feeling is numb.  I have spent the last few months of my life completely at war with my desire to lie in bed and never get up again.  Every morning I wake up and spend about 45 minutes convincing myself it’s worth it.  On days when my stomach is acting up, that time is extended.  And there have been a lot of days of failure.  I’ve missed classes.  I’ve ignored text messages and emails.  I’ve skipped meals.  I’ve spent days basking in the relentless meaninglessness of my own existence, knowing for a fact that nothing I do matters and I will eventually die so why not today.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And your gut reaction will be to tell me this isn’t true.  It’ll get better.  It’s happened already.  Friends telling me they love me and they’re here for me and they’ll talk when I need to.  Here’s the problem.  In those moments, I don’t want to talk to you.  Anything you say to me is meaningless.  Your love is meaningless.  Your love can even be harmful.  I am such a basket of pain and numbness and anxiey that your attempt to intervene can throw me out of a very delicate balance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Medications calm the chaos.  Medications allow me to get out of bed more days than I normally could.  But they don’t cure that feeling.  They make it all a little fuzzier and distant.  Numb in a good way.  It’s an angry numbness though.  It’s buzzing and itching.  It’s a skin that doesn’t exactly fit.  It’s screaming fuck you at the car behind you that honks their horn for no reason.  It’s sitting up at night crying without knowing why.  It’s letting your body waste away because it’s easier than dealing with the physical illness that will eventually kill you.  It&#8217;s wondering how long it actually takes to starve to death.  It’s wondering why your significant other loves you enough to watch you go through all this and stick around.  It’s staring at the ceiling wondering how you could possibly tell me I could make my life better.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And it becomes manageable, but it certainly doesn’t get better.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/20/It-Gets-Better.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/20/It-Gets-Better.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category><category><![CDATA[Depression]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Day in the Life]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Today I am hungry.  Today I am nauseous.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I was thinking about it just now, and I’ve never really considered how different my life is now that I’m sick and have been diagnosed.  Obviously, life has changed.  You don’t gain a chronic illness and go back to life as usual unless you are very very lucky.  Illness almost always has a permanent effect on you and your way of life, and you don’t realize it until you get sick.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Which is actually why I’m writing this.  As I said in my previous post, most of my friends consider me cured.  I seem to live a normal life, I seem mentally and physically able bodied, and I seem happy.  I am none of those things.  If you are unfamiliar with the Spoon Theory, now would be a good time to google it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Take today for example.  This morning I woke up extra nauseous.  This morning at precisely 1:34 am.  I know the time because I grabbed my phone on the way to the bathroom, expecting to be in there waiting to vomit for a while.  However, as soon as I got out of bed and walked to my bedroom door, the sensation vanished completely.  I shrugged and got back into bed, spent a little time getting comfortable and started drifting back to sleep.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is a completely normal occurrence.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Most nights, it stops there and I simply sleep for the rest of the night.  Otherwise, what happens next is a series of unfortunate events.  I spent the next few hours of the morning almost falling asleep, waking up to nausea or abdominal cramps, walking to the bathroom door, and going back to bed without ever actually entering the bathroom.  It is now 5:24 am.  I am excessively tired and finally fall asleep until my alarm goes off at 7:00 am.  I have gotten about 4 hours of actual sleep.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is a completely normal night.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This series doesn’t happen every night, or even most nights.  It’s a number somewhere between a third and half.  Not enough for my doctors to consider it a problem, but enough to have entered into my new normal.  You’ll notice I didn’t mention any form of the words “confusion” or “frustration” in that description.  Because on these nights I don’t feel those emotions.  I go into autopilot and walk about my “morning routine” as much as necessary until my body feels like allowing me to sleep, and then I do.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I should say here that I don’t ever actually vomit.  Though one of the symptoms of gastroparesis is excessive vomiting, my version doesn’t give me that relief.  I’m told this is normal.  I’m also told the people who spend most of their days vomiting don’t get any relief from the action anyway.  That is to say, vomiting doesn’t make the nausea any better.  At any rate, I don’t actually vomit.  I just go to the bathroom as a safety precaution.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Anyway, it is now 7:00 am, I have gotten 4ish hours of sleep and I have about an hour and a half to get ready for school.  My first action is to take two pills, one for nausea and one for anxiety.  I then assess the results of the previous night’s activities.  I didn’t sleep enough and am therefore too nauseous to eat breakfast.  This will trigger my anxiety.  If I eat, I will be more nauseous, experience extreme abdominal pains, and later likely have diarrhea.  My morning nausea pill will do almost nothing today.  I have to take it anyway.  It keeps my digestive system stimulated and because of it maybe I will get lunch later.  I get up to make tea, set an alarm for about an hour, and lay back down to rest.  This hour is the one I normally spend eating breakfast, showering, doing makeup, and any other things I do on good days.  Because today is a bad day, I have fewer spoons and need the extra rest.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now here’s the kicker.  All bad nights result in bad days, but not all bad days are a result of bad nights.  That is to say a third to half of my nights are bad, but a little over half of my days are bad.  I don’t always get the warning.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The rest of the day follows a similar pattern.  I go to class and attempt to pay attention despite wanting to fall back asleep in my chair.  At lunch time, I take a second nausea pill and reassess.  I am tired, anxious, still too nauseous to eat, and running out of spoons.  After noon some time, my body realizes I haven’t consumed anything but tea since I woke up and my stomach starts growling.  I am still too nauseous to eat.  I have to let it grumble and move on with the day.  This will trigger my anxiety.  I work on school work.  I don’t get to take a nap.  I take pills for anxiety and depression.  I reassess.  I am very tired, my attention is wandering, my stomach is growling, I am nauseous, and I am out of spoons.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I have one class left to attend.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If I attend class tonight I will sit in a chair for an hour and a half daydreaming.  If I don’t attend class, it will be the third time in a row I have missed that class.  Both will trigger my anxiety.  Either way I will be tired, my mind will be wandering, my stomach will be growling, I will be nauseous and anxious, and I will be into tomorrow’s spoons.  I will reassess after class.  I will take my nausea pill.  I will likely still be too nauseous to eat.  My hands will start shaking if they haven’t already.  This will trigger my anxiety.  I will take a bevy of pills for nausea, depression, and anxiety and attempt to sleep.  I will end the day exhausted, mind numb, shaking, anxious, stomach growling, and out of spoons for tomorrow as well.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And I will be nauseous.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is a completely normal day.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/16/A-Day-in-the-Life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/16/A-Day-in-the-Life.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category><category><![CDATA[Bodily Functions]]></category><category><![CDATA[Spoon Theory]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Living on Borrowed Time]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>As I write this, my hands are shaking.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I reentered FaceBook society today after taking a mental health break.  In the wake of our questionable President-Elect, I have been forced to reorganize my though processes concerning the next four years of my life.  It is no secret Mr. Trump is no fan of disabled persons and I have no doubt that extends to people of any kind of mental and physical health problems.  You can’t really expect a person who claims pregnant women are an inconvenience to employers to have any sympathy for those of us with chronic and sometimes debilitating illnesses.  It has already been hard to plan with an unpredictable disease like gastroparesis.  Now I am trying to factor in variables like cuts to public health programs, the loss of the Affordable Care Act, and rising prescription drug prices under a regime that has expressed no interest in curbing them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I saw a post today about a young girl being fitted for leg braces as a result of a disease that will likely take her life in the next 4 years.  The point of the post wasn’t “isn’t my daughter’s life sad” though.  It was “my daughter will need these public health funding programs that Republicans are threatening to cut in the very near future”.  Everyone keeps telling those dependent on such programs to just get out there and vote for a better candidate next election.  As if that were possible.  As if we had the time.  We can’t wait 4 years for a better president.  We need one now.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Many of my friends have commented on what an improvement my health has made recently.  “You got so skinny for a while.”  “We were so worried about you.”  “I’m so glad you’re better now.”  I have a secret to tell you all.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My health will be short-lived.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You see, almost all of my recent gains have come as a result of a drug called Reglan.  If you don’t shudder at the sight of that name, that’s fine.  It’s marketed as a short-term solution to nausea, vomiting, GERD, and is even sometimes given to pregnant women to help with the production of breast milk.  What Reglan does is stimulate the nerves and muscles of the digestive system in order to help you digest food more efficiently and quickly.  A miracle for someone whose stomach doesn’t digest food at all on its own.  Why don’t we hand this out like candy?  Cure sufferers of chronic stomach ailments once and for all?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Reglan doesn’t start causing problems until you are taking it long term.  “Long term” here means more than a few weeks.  It starts with increased anxiety and nervousness and escalates into full on Parkinson’s-like tremors and muscle movements.  An irreversible neurological disorder call Tardive Dyskinesia.  Symptoms include tremors and shaking in the extremities, facial twitching and grimacing, random movements of the limbs, and difficulty breathing.  Unmistakably linked to use of neuroleptics, antipsychotics, and drugs like Reglan.  In fact, multiple doctors have told me Reglan has an unusually high chance of producing Tardive Dyskinesia over the long term.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve been on it for over a year.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>For starters, I didn’t feel like starving to death at the ripe old age of 22.  But also, there exists a percentage of Reglan users with gastroparesis who never develop complications.  I spoke to someone who’s been on it for 8 years without a problem and I spoke to someone who developed symptoms the day she started taking it.  So you don’t really know.  Maybe you win the lottery or maybe this game of Russian Roulette puts a bullet in you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My point in all this is there is a very high probability of me needing to quit my miracle drug in the near future.  If I’m going to develop symptoms, I’m going to do it soon.  I’ve goon too long without side effects.  My doctors are considering taking me off before I develop symptoms to begin with.  For them, the chances of possibly irreversible damage are too high.  I still prefer not to starve to death.  But if you paid attention to my introductory post, you know what happens to me when my stomach isn’t medicated.  If you know me in real life, you got to witness years of it up close.  And my window is closing right as our loving Republican party is threatening to defund and take away the very health programs and insurance policies that will keep me alive.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We don’t have 4 years and we don’t have the option of hoping Mr. Trump’s policies overlook us in the coming reign.  We are going to need help and we are going to need it soon.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And, as I write this, my hands are shaking.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/11/Living-on-Borrowed-Time.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/11/Living-on-Borrowed-Time.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category><category><![CDATA[Donald Trump]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[About Me]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>So this is my blog.  I&#8217;ve spent a lot of time thinking about starting one, wondering what I would share, and how I would go about saying it.  Mostly, though, this exists for my sanity, and anything I write will be for the purpose of preserving my sanity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I was born on November 9th of a year I will not specify.  For most of my life, I&#8217;ve been fairly normal and healthy.  Maybe I didn&#8217;t get along with everyone, and maybe I suffered some childhood traumas that needed a little therapy to work through, but I was nothing out of the ordinary.  And yes, I consider needing a little therapy at some point ordinary.  I did well in school, got accepted into the accelerated programs at all levels, took some Advanced Placement classes and eventually graduated with a respectable GPA and many college prospects.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My problems began so slowly I didn&#8217;t really recognize them at first.  You see, because my parents couldn&#8217;t afford to send me to the schools I wanted to attend (something I will <strong>never</strong> blame them for), I took a year and a half off to "find myself" (essentially do whatever I wanted) before entering my local City College to get my shit together.  It took me a while to figure out my major, and I jumped from Chemistry, to Linguistics, to Foreign Languages, before settling on English Literature.  It made sense when I finally got there.  What do I love more than anything?  Reading and writing.  Why not get a degree in it?  All the while I was watching my friends essentially speed past me, get degrees, get employed, get married, etc. while I kinda&#8230;&#8203; sat.  If you asked me then, I would have said I&#8217;m going at my own pace and fuck you if you have a problem with it.  It was nice.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Midway through June of 2013, I woke up nauseous.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Looking back, this wasn&#8217;t the start of my anxiety disorder.  It was just the proverbial straw.  The start was that pesky trauma I mentioned, followed by not being able to go to college, followed by watching everyone around my basically live their lives without me.  It all built up into this little ball inside me that I wasn&#8217;t recognizing.  And then I woke up nauseous.  And then I stayed nauseous.  And then my doctor told me I had ulcers.  And then acid reflux.  And then a bacterial infection. And a bowel disorder. And IBS. And allergies. And then&#8230;&#8203; nothing.  I went through 12 doctors, untold tests and procedures, medications galor, side effects, and none of them helped.  I went from 160 pounds to 95 in 6 months.  I lived on rice and potatoes for a year.  They finally found a medication that stabilized me, but nothing made the nausea go away.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So I gave up on the doctors and I gave up on my health and I let myself deteriorate and just continued on with school.  I developed serious perfectionism, then paranoia, germaphobia, all of which bloomed into Generalized Anxiety Disorder and Depressive episodes.  My life imploded, and I let it.  I began a slow spiral into insanity and all the little things I had ignored about my life came back to haunt me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In May of 2015 I was accepted to The University of California Berkeley.  In August of 2015 I was diagnosed with Gastroparesis.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Gastroparesis is the weakening or total paralysis of the stomach muscles.  The symptoms are nausea, vomiting, stomach and abdominal pains, constipation, acid reflux, loss of appitite, and weight loss.  It can be caused by diabetes, cancer, botched abdominal surgeries, certain auto-immune disorders, complications of viral infections, and old age.  I had all of those symptoms and none of those causes.  I fall into the 10-15% of cases that present idiopathic.  No known cause.  No cure.  The only treatments are certain medications that can speed the emptying of the stomach, block nausea receptors in the brain, and calm the stomach acid.  And I finally got help.  Not just with my stomach, but with my anxiety and depression.  I found an answer, I found a reason to keep going, and, with the help of my now-fiancé, I found a psychiatrist.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Now, over a year later, I also have this.  A place to come with my struggles and anxieties.  This is not a happy story with a happy ending unfortunately.  My diagnosis brought more anxiety and stress.  Attending Cal, a top university, multiplied it.  I am in a place where I don&#8217;t know what to do or where to go from here.  There are no more answers to find, just the next treatment and the next day.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I guess, while accepting the risk of sounding cheesy, I hope to help others like me.  This battle has encompassed me, body and mind.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And I am not alone.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/08/About-Me.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thelifeoffetzig.com/2016/11/08/About-Me.html</guid><category><![CDATA[About Me]]></category><category><![CDATA[Introduction]]></category><category><![CDATA[Gastroparesis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mental Illness]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>